# XIAOZHE YAO

Phone: +41 779443261 xiaozhe.yaoi@gmail.com

Zurich, Switzerland

### CAREER GOALS

My longterm career goal is to become a researcher and engineer in machine learning infrastructures and apply machine learning to solve problems in other fields (e.g databases, social sciences, etc). I am thrilled to help other developers use machine learning in a more efficient, simple way. By working on the ML infrastructure, we could not only boost the application of machine learning but also investigate which algorithm is better than others. I am convinced that general-purpose, full-lifecycle management of machine learning could help researchers, companies and individuals achieve their goals more easily.

#### EDUCATION

MS University of Zurich, Data Science

Sept 19 - June 21

Thesis: TBD Advisor: TBD

Minor in Mathematics

Micro Master Massachusetts Institute of Technology

Sept 20 - Dec 21

Statistics and Data Science

**BS** Shenzhen University, Computer Science

Sept 13 - June 17

With honour in High-Performance Computing

Thesis: Face Detection with Multi-Block Local Binary Pattern in OpenCV

Advisor: Prof. Dr Shiqi Yu

### Honors, Awards & Grants

# **Excellent Youth Entrepreneur of Nanshan, Shenzhen**

2017

### **Loongson Scholarship (Third Prize)**

2015

Awarded to students with excellent academic records, also known as Chinese Academy of Sciences Fellow Awards

### **Cyberport Creative Micro Fund, Hong Kong**

2016

### Individual Makers Fund, Shenzhen Sci. & Tech. Committee

2016

Grants for Students Ideas and Prototype, Completed

#### PROJECT & EXPERIENCE

## Associate Founder, AICAMP.CO.,LTD, Hong Kong

2019-Present

• <u>AID</u>. I created an open-source system for publishing, discovering, deploying, optimizing and monitoring deep learning models.

**Research Assistant**, CVLab, Shenzhen University, Shenzhen, China 2018-2019 Advisor: Prof. Dr Shiqi Yu

• *Industry AI*. We created a computer vision platform for online labelling, training, and testing.

Bachelor Thesis, CVLab, Shenzhen University, Shenzhen, China

2017

Advisor: Prof. Dr Shiqi Yu

Multi-Block Local Binary Pattern in OpenCV. I modified the Multi-Block Local
Binary Pattern from Prof. Shiqi Yu's version and integrated it into a fork of OpenCV.
I learned the traditional face detection process, especially Viola-Jones's algorithm
(haar-like features, cascade classifier and AdaBoost) and LBP related algorithms
from this thesis

# SIAT, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Shenzhen

2017 - 2018

Data Scientist Intern, Precision Medicine Lab

• Foodie - Healthy and Diet Food Recommendation. We developed a recommendation system to help users take their taste and body conditions into consideration for eating. I learned and implemented the recommendation system based on the wide and deep model from TensorFlow, crawled the nutrition data and built the backend.

#### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Universität Zürich, Zürich

2020 - 2021

**Teaching Assistant**,

Informatics-1 (Intro to Programming and Data-Oriented Programming)
Informatics-2 (data structures and algorithms)

Shenzhen University, Shenzhen

2014 to 2017

**Teaching Assistant**, Computer Science Department

Professional English
Web Programming

Internet Application Development (Android)

Data Structure and Algorithms

Java Programming

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

# Conference Papers

(Peer-Reviewed)

Chen, Yingying, and Xiaozhe Yao. "CVTron Web: A Versatile Framework for Online Computer Vision Services." World Congress on Services. Springer, Cham, 2018.

Yao, Xiaozhe, Chen Yingying and Rongjie Liao. "Face Based Advertisement Recommendation with Deep Learning: A Case Study." International Conference on Smart Computing and Communication. Springer, Cham, 2017.

# Conference Workshop Papers

Xiaozhe Yao "MLPM: Machine Learning Package Manager." MLSys 2020 Workshop for MLOps System.

## COMMUNITY SERVICE

# **IAPR TC4 Winter School on Biometrics 2019**

Photographer, Shenzhen, 13-17 Jan 2019

### LANGUAGES

Chinese: Native Language

English: CEFR C1, Effective Operational Proficiency